[Music]
what's up everyone
it's good to be with you again welcome
to episode 13
of ask a budget today i answer your
questions about astrophysics space
and the universe and as always you guys
have asked me a great
great deal of questions very interesting
questions and i have picked
a bunch of questions out of those which
hopefully represents a wide spectrum of
topics
that will cover the whole range of
issues
in astrophysics and cosmology and space
and the universe so let's get right into
it
with question number one
so aditya asks can gamma ray bursts
and magnetars wipe out the entire life
from the earth
that's a good question so let's first
discuss what gamma ray bursts are what
are magnetars
so a magnetar is in it's it's a neutron
star
that has an extremely powerful magnetic
field
what's a neutron star a neutron star is
the collapsed
stellar core of a super giant star that
went supernova
and it that the parent star typically
has a mass of about 10 to 25 solar
masses
and the neutron star typically has
a mass of about 1.4 solar masses
and a radius of about 10 kilometers so
it's an extremely dense
extremely compact object and a magnetar
is a
highly magnetized neutron star it has an
extremely powerful
magnetic field typically about a hundred
million times the strength of the most
powerful
man-made uh artificial magnet so that's
what a magnetar is
now are magnetized responsible for
gamma-ray bursts not really
those are not the real pre progenitors
of
ray bursts so let's go into what is a
gamma ray burst
a gamma ray burst is the gamma ray
bursts are some of the most
energetic events in the entire universe
so it's a very powerful flash of light
mostly gamma rays and the luminosity the
like
the amount of light that is emitted so
it emits about
in it emits in just about 10 seconds or
so
more light than the entire sun
will emit during its entire lifetime so
that's how
incredibly energetic a gamma ray burst
is so typically there are three
different kinds of gamma ray bursts
very short duration gamma gamma ray
bursts typically of the order of
milliseconds
then there are medium to long duration
gamma ray bursts from
about a second to about 10 seconds to
maybe 100 seconds
and then there are longer duration gamma
ray bursts so the ones we are talking
about the vast majority of gamma ray
bursts
are these uh short duration medium
duration ones
but 10 seconds or so long approximately
10 to 100 seconds
typically 10 seconds or so so
how are these gamma ray bursts uh formed
what or
what is the origin typically it's the
supernova explosion
of of a supergiant star so that's
typically what
gives rise to these gamma ray bursts
that are of the order of 10 seconds long
and when a star like this goes supernova
it emits
these uh these beams of light so let me
show you what it looks like
uh so this is an artist's representation
of a gamma ray burst
it is a star that has gone supernova and
it's emitting
two beams of radiation in opposite
directions
it's aligned along the axis of rotation
of the star
so that's what it typically looks like
these are extremely energetic beams of
radiation
uh it contains all kinds of radiation
but typically the most powerful so
the most significant component is gamma
rays
the explosion also gives off lots of
neutrinos and things but these two
collimated beams of
of radiation are mostly composed of
gamma rays so let's go into
what are gamma rays so gamma rays are
the most energetic
elect form of electromagnetic radiation
it's a penetrating kind of
electromagnetic radiation
uh a gamma ray typically has
millions of possibly millions of times
more energy than
visible light and its wavelength is
extremely short so
the consequence of this is that you
cannot reflect gamma rays of mirrors
the wavelength is so short that it goes
right through mirrors
it goes right through living tissue and
it can cause a great deal of radiation
damage to
to living tissues which is why these are
extremely hazardous
uh light rays so these are invisible
obviously
and they can cause a lot of damage
typically
you need to shield yourself from gamma
rays using something like lead which is
very thick and which is a great
uh amount of density so gamma rays are
on earth
emitted from various radiation processes
from the
from the radioactive decay of atomic
nuclei
etc and that's what you find in nuclear
reactors so that's why you need all this
radiation shielding
so it's very dangerous to human beings
it can cause damage to your dna to your
bone marrow
to internal organs so that's why it's
very hazardous
so this uh event so how was it
discovered
so in the 1960s the americans sent up
satellites
uh in earth orbit and the purpose of the
satellites the villa satellites
was to detect uh nuclear tests anywhere
on the planet
so a nuclear test usually has a very
typical signature it's a double flash
signature it's a very powerful initial
flash of light
then it is followed by a slower and and
increase gradually increasing uh after
glow
of radiation so it's a very interesting
very typical double flash event
so that's what these uh satellites the
villa satellites were designed to detect
and they were equipped with with x-ray
detectors gamma-ray detectors
and other such instruments so what these
instruments
what these satellites found was they
found strange
flashes of gamma rays strange gamma ray
bursts
coming from outer space and there was no
possible
there was no explanation for that at the
time and this was a classified
uh deal these satellites were classified
the data was classified so it was not
revealed
to the scientific world until the mid or
early 1970s
by which time it was found that these
events happen from time to time
in outer space eventually it was
detected that these are extra galactic
events these
events don't happen in the milky way
they occur very very far away in far-off
galaxies
and the distribution is isotropic which
means it doesn't come from any
particular
direction in space it's spread all over
so now we have a better understanding
the gamma ray bursts we are referring to
the short to medium duration ones uh
they
are they originate in these supernova
explosions of
uh of these supergiant stars
so there are two beams of light so if
the earth were to come
in the path of one of these beams it
could affect the earth if the gamma ray
burst was nearby maybe within
a thousand light years or so or maybe
less
so if it is at a reasonable distance
from the earth it can definitely
uh cause cause some changes
on the earth the first thing is if a
gamma ray burst were to hit the earth
straight on one of the beams
then within seconds it will destroy a
significant portion of the ozone layer
of the earth so at least half of the
ozone layer will be gone within
seconds and it will not affect
the surface it will not have an effect
on the surface of the earth directly or
immediately
but it will wipe out significant
portions of the ozone layer
and that will cause a great influx of
ultraviolet radiation
on the surface of the planet which will
have dangerous and bad effects on life
on life on the earth and also the
destruction of the ozone will also
have a different effect in the chemistry
of the atmosphere
it will react with nitrogen it will
cause it will create
nitrous oxides and dioxides which are
gases that have a long-term cooling
effect because they
they produce a kind of smog that covers
the planet
so you could have a kind of uh
an induced winter the kind of winter you
have after after
an asteroid impact event that sort of
thing
so it will have long-term effects it
won't have immediate effects on
on life but it could possibly and
conceivably cause a mass extinction
event of some type
so it is believed that some mass
extinctions in the past
may have possibly been triggered off by
a gamma-ray burst event
so that is the answer it can possibly
affect life on earth but most likely
such a gamma-ray burst would have to be
directly aimed at the earth which would
be a very
well it would be just bad luck if that
would happen and it would need to be
somewhere within our own galaxy because
it needs to be close by
for the uh intensity of the beam to be
to be significant enough to cause all
this damage
so yes possibly it can it definitely has
the potential
to cause significant damage to the earth
i don't think it can wipe out the entire
life of the earth but it can certainly
trigger off an extinction evil event
on some scale so that's the answer it's
a good question
this is from meenakshi in a session you
explained about cosmic strings and that
all galaxies might be connected
through them maybe from the supermassive
black holes at the center
but as the universe expands and these
galaxies go far away from us
will they still be attached to the
strings do the strings
expand as well also can one galaxy be
connected to more than one galaxies
at a time and it was after a video okay
so what i referred to is uh cosmic
strings which are a kind of topological
defect
let's not go into what that is it's
essentially a defect in space-time
itself it's a wrinkle in space time so
to say
so according to string theory these
uh cosmic strings topological defects
could have been
created in enormous quantities in the
very initial moments after the big bang
so these are defects in the fabric of
space-time itself these are wrinkles in
space-time
let me illustrate what it means so let's
say you have a cosmic string
it's maybe one atomic diameter thick
it's very very thin very
very thin but it is a wrinkle in
space-time
so if you have a cosmic string this way
and you want to take a
you want to start from point a and go
all the way around it and
return to point a then you will find
that you have not traversed
360 degrees you have traversed a
distance that is less than 360 degrees
because this is a wrinkle in space-time
itself it
it warps and and distorts space-time
so going around it you will find that
you have traversed less than 360 degrees
and still you have reached the initial
point so that's the kind of defect
it is in space time itself and it is a
warping of
space time a wrinkle
and these effects also cause gravitation
because
gravitation is the curvature of
space-time so cosmic strings are massive
they have mass they have gravitational
effects they can cause gravitational
lensing
they can split a star into if we are
looking at it through a cosmic spring
etc so that's the kind of effect a
cosmic string has do
uh have we found any thus far we have
thus far not
observed any evidence of cosmic strings
but it is a possibility
these may exist and like i said these
emerged
these may have been created in the
initial very initial phase after the big
bang and as the universe expanded these
strings stretched out in all directions
and they would still be around so these
cosmic strings would be
probably be larger longer than the
radius or diameter of the observable
universe it's possible yes
and these are very tightly stretched
strings they are vibrating and causing
gravitational effects
if they exist so that's what a cosmic
string is
now i uh what's believed by some people
is that uh
cosmic strings could basically be at the
center of wormholes
so every cosmic string would have a
wormhole around it and these wormholes
would would remain open because of the
presence of the cosmic string
within typically a wormhole is something
that snaps
shut because of the way space-time is
space-time wants
a wormhole if it can be created to
immediately snap shut
and pinch off so it's very hard to have
a wormhole that remains open that you
can
actually traverse it so that's the
einstein rosen bridge
that snaps shut immediately almost
immediately it wants a snapshot
so the main problem with wormholes is to
create a traversable wormhole
and for that you need something like
negative mass or something which will
repel
space-time and you know keep the
wormhole open so that sort of
substance doesn't really exist as far as
we know but a solution
could be these ancient topological
defects called cosmic strings those
could keep wormholes open
now the other thing is that some
physicists
believe that these uh supermassive black
holes that are at the center of most
galaxies
these could actually possibly be
wormholes portals to another dimension
or to another region not to another
dimension but to another region in
space-time maybe a far-off region
so it could connect two very distant
regions of space time and you could
traverse this wormhole
and reach the other location almost in
very little time
and if there are cosmic stings there are
strings that are threaded through these
wormholes then maybe that's what keeps
them open
so this is all hypothetical we have no
evidence of it
but theoretical physics does allow this
sort of
an eventuality so that is essentially
what i was referring to
uh if these uh supermassive black holes
are actually
wormholes now can one galaxy be
connected to more than
one galaxy at a time we don't know it is
it may be possible it may not be
possible
if it's a wormhole will it definitely
have at least one
location to which it is connected can a
wormhole connect to two
more than one place at a time i'm not
sure that is possible
but at least there's a one to one
opening uh one to one correspondence
between one wormhole
between the opening and the exit of a
wormhole so that's in short about this
question it's an interesting question
but
like i said we have never actually
observed we don't have any observational
evidence of cosmic strings
people have been looking for them
primarily by the gravitational lensing
effects they would have
because mass basically warps
mass the presence of mass makes
light travel in curves so light is no
longer able to
go in a straight line when you have mass
the the path of life
light itself is curved so that causes
this effect called gravitational lensing
in which
stars and galaxies are seen from the
earth
as being distorted in shape because of
the presence of some mass
between us and that particular star or
galaxy
so if a cosmic string is between us
directly between us and a star
then maybe we could see a star split in
two for some time
so people have been trying to look for
that but thus far we have found
no evidence maybe it means that these
may be quite rare
or maybe few and far between because the
universe has expanded to such a great
extent
that this initial collection of cosmic
strings has gone off in all directions
so maybe it's hard to observe and as i
say it's very thin
and that could be another reason so
we don't know if they really exist but
according to string theory these
could exist and this could have been
formed in the
early universe and they could still be
around so that's the answer
good question
sharias asks why are all planets and
stars
round why not square or triangular
rectangle it's a silly question but i'm
very curious and this education system
kills curious minds it's not a silly
question it's a great question
it goes to the heart of what gravity is
so that's what we find everywhere we
look
all planets that we know of are roughly
spherical
whether it's these are rocky planets or
gaseous planets like jupiter saturn etc
even most of the even all of the moons
or most of the moons that we know in our
solar system
are roughly spherical the asteroids that
we observe
are of all shapes right and sizes
most of them are not spherical except
the very largest
asteroids like iris probably there is
this uh
planetesimal or planetoid in the uh
trans in the in orbit beyond pluto it's
called
haumea i think which is oblong in shape
so it is not very large
and if we look around the universe all
stars are spherical our own star the sun
is spherical
and exoplanets that we have discovered
are also
spherical so what's the reason for this
right that's the question
so the reason is gravity gravity is a
force
so if you have a an object gravity is
something that
is concentrated in its center of mass so
every object has a center of mass
and the effective mass of that object is
concentrated you can
it can be thought of as being
concentrated in that center of mass
and the larger an object gets the more
powerful
its self-gravitation is
and this gravity tries to create the
most
efficient shape possible by pulling all
parts of the object towards the center
and the most efficient shape is a
perfect sphere
now when an object is small then its
atomic structure its molecular structure
the bonds within the molecules etcetera
they overpower the force of gravity and
therefore it retains
its shape right so the everyday objects
in our life
they have non-spherical shapes because
the uh
the other forces overpower the force of
gravity which is the weakest force that
we know of
but when you have an object that is
large enough around a thousand
kilometers
or so in uh radius then you find that
the force of gravity eventually
overcomes all of this
you will still have chunks of rock and
all that are of all different
shapes and sizes but the overall shape
of the object becomes
more and more uh idealized
it tends towards becoming a proper
sphere
that's because the mass the the
mass essentially is concentrated in a
way
at the center of the object in the in
the center of mass and everything is
pulled towards that
because of the force of gravity that's
why it overly that that's why it
eventually over time especially if it's
large enough it slowly coalesces into a
into a spherical shape so that's very
easy to see in
in gas gas planets gaseous planets like
jupiter saturn
uranus neptune etc and even when you
have
rocky planets like the earth and venus
etc
because of the large size the the the
force of gravity overpowers the other
forces
and arranges the distribution of matter
in a roughly spherical shape
so even today the earth is not perfectly
spherical
it's like a squashed it's like a
squashed sphere
it has bulges etc but overall from far
it does look more or less spherical
so that is the reason why uh planets are
not triangular or rectangle
a planet has to be something that whose
internal gravity forces it to assume a
spherical straight that's one of the
definitions of
a planet so that's what it is uh it's
the
effect of gravity that causes this
spherical shape to
to emerge over time especially if the
object is large enough then it will very
quickly become spherical
if it is smaller then it may take some
time but today
the solar system is about four and a
half billion years old so everything has
become spherical
whatever could and that's the answer to
your question that's a that's a good
question it's not a silly question
akash asks what are solar sails
can we build one uh in large enough to
transport humans and what are the speeds
it can attain
and how will it help us once we get
further
away from the sun so a solar sail
is a technology that could uh become a
reality very soon
so it is essentially a very thin very
light
sail like structure typically made of a
very highly reflective material
metal usually and it essentially works
by the transfer of momentum
from the electromagnetic field into the
the
sail itself so it basically gets a
physical impulse from the
uh from photons hitting it so that's
what a solar
solar shell is sail is it's it
it works on the base because of
radiation pressure
so radiation like light effects of
physical pressure
on objects especially highly reflective
objects
especially objects that are that are
very light
so let me show you what a solar sail
looks like
so this is an artist's uh depiction or
representation of a solar sail
it's a very thin uh
structure very light and and it's highly
reflective
so there is this uh there is a project
being uh
which is underway right now it's called
breakthrough star
shot so this project
hopes to use this solar sail technology
and send very small probes
all the way to our nearest star which is
uh alpha centauri and
there is a this exoplanet around this
this star system
which is called proxima centauri b so
this project hopes to send
a large number of probes to this planet
of using this technology so these will
be very small probes maybe
a gram or two in size these are like
basically chips
computer chips but they will have some
instruments on them
very basic instruments which would
hopefully once they reach there be able
to send us data or images back
uh to earth so the technology is that we
will have about a thousand of these
probes
each solar cell will be a few meters
across
and it will contain this little uh chip
sized
uh nano satellite or nanoprobe of sorts
and these will be will be accelerated to
about
15 to 20 percent of the speed of light
using lasers
so either ground-based lasers or
space-based lasers in orbit around the
earth
will will fire beams of laser light at
these probes one by one
and within five to ten minutes
accelerate them to around
15 to 20 of the speed of light and
that's how these
thousand or so probes will go all the
way to that star system
why thousand because many of them could
get destroyed or damaged on
on the way because of impacts with
cosmic dust
so that's why a thousand of these probes
will be sufficient
hopefully to reach there at least a few
of them in one piece and send back some
useful data to us
so this should be able to reach there if
we do it today
in about 20 to 30 years
and then another four and a four or so
lighty four or so years for us to get
the signals back
from there so this is a technology that
is
almost possible we need some
improvements in our existing technology
to make it possible
but it could be this this project would
actually take off in about a decade or
so from today
so this is a very uh a technology that
is very much feasible
it's only a decade or so away from today
we need to improve certain
engineering and technology technological
features
but it's very possible right now we are
in a position to send these very small
tiny
probes to another star system but in the
future as the technology improves we
should
we could very well be possible it could
very well will be possible to send human
beings
as well which means basically you may
have larger spacecraft
which can hold humans or a number of
humans
which could be transported on the basis
of
this solar sail or photon sail or light
sail
technology so that's what us that's what
a light sail is
it's a very interesting technology it is
very much
feasible and it could happen soon so
it's one of the ways one could uh
travel across uh space it can
uh it can transport
uh payloads to a significant percentage
of the speed of light
10 to 15 to even 20 percent possibly so
that's the so that's the best we could
have as of now because chemical rockets
can't
attain such speeds so this is the best
technology
or potential technology that we have as
of today that could enable us to cross
interstellar space and reach another
star system
so interesting very interesting
technology
okay gaurav asks what is the temperature
of the moon
and why does it fluctuate so much
so the moon the temperature of the moon
like you said it fluctuates a lot
when see the moon rotates around its
axis
once in about 27 days so about 13 and a
half days
each side of the moon is in sunlight and
about 13
and a half days it is in the darkness so
the day is 13 and a half days long
and the night is 13 and a half earth
days long
so when sunlight is incident on the
moon's surface the temperature is about
123 or so degrees
celsius and when the surface is in
darkness
the temperatures goes down the
temperature goes down to about minus
170 something degrees
celsius 173 or 75 or thereabouts
so that's the kind of temperature range
you have and the moment sunlight
it turns off when the moon rotates and
the sunlight is no longer
available then it almost immediately
goes from 127
to minus 173 degrees almost
instantaneously
so why does this happen it's because the
moon has no real atmosphere whatsoever
on the earth we have this atmosphere
which traps heat
and that's why you have a much milder
change
that's why you have much milder and much
gentler changes
in temperature the seasons as well as
day and night you have only a few
degrees of difference between day and
night
typically on the moon it's it's a
tremendous difference between day and
night
day and night it's because of the lack
of any
any real atmosphere on the moon's
surface
there is a very thin tenuous atmosphere
a few atoms and molecules zipping around
the total mass of the atmosphere of the
moon maybe
10 metric tons or so so it is it is
extreme
it's basically negligible you can regard
it as a proper vacuum
the surface of the moon so that is the
reason why
the temperature is the changes in
temperature are so drastic between day
and night on the moon
because there is no atmosphere which
traps heat
so that's the answer good question
okay aditya asks a very good question
what is the theory of relativity
so the theory of relativity essentially
is a theory of gravitation a theory of
gravity
so the relativity came in two phases in
1905 albert einstein
put forth the special theory of
relativity and in
a decade later after a great deal of
work he put forth the
general theory of relativity so the
general theory of relativity builds upon
the the very baby steps he took in the
special theory of relativity
so i'll talk about the general theory of
relativity which is the main which is
what
relativity actually is so
until this theory came came around we
had
we understood gravity reasonably well we
had the newtonian theory of gravity
which sees gravity as a force a force
that acts at a distance it force
a force that acts at infinite distances
instantaneously
so it's an instantaneous force no matter
how far you are from
a massive object you will feel its
gravity no matter how far you are you'll
feel it instantaneously
that is how newton's law of gravitation
works
if you can see the equation so that is
how we understood gravity now
general relativity says that gravity is
not a force it is the geometry of space
itself
it is the curvature of space time mass
causes the
fabric of space and time space time to
curve
and this curvature is what we interpret
as gravity as the is this so-called
as this apparent force of gravity
so according to this theory the entire
fabric of the universe is a four
dimensional fabric it's called
space-time
three dimensions of space and one
dimension of time
all integrated together and that is what
we are
immersed in that is the stage or the
arena upon which the universe
exists so that's space time
and everything in the in space time has
a limit a speed speed limit which is the
speed of light
so that is something that's hard coded
in the universe nothing can travel
faster than the speed of light
not even these ripples in space time
themselves even these ripples in space
time will only travel
at the speed of time at the speed of
light i'm sorry and not
beyond that so that is a very
interesting uh
effect it is it's a it's a very very
significant difference from what newton
said
so let me illustrate this by doing a
thought experiment
so this here is a
a toy model of our solar system
we have the sun at the center and all
the planets around it the sun should be
much smaller but you get the point
so according to newton's theory this
star at the center right the star at the
center here
it exerts a force an attractive force
on all of the planets and it's an
instantaneous force
it's a force that acts all the way out
to infinity now let's assume for a
second that
let's do this thought experiment let's
suddenly switch off the sun the sun
suddenly disappears all of a sudden
for whatever reason it's a thought
experiment they can do anything so let's
assume that i
switch off the sun i make it disappear
then what happens
these planets are all going round round
mostly round
around the sun and since the sun
disappears
this force it was exerting on all the
planets instantaneously disappears
and what will happen is all the planets
will fly off in all directions
right that's what will happen
instantaneously at the same time all the
planets will disappear
will go off in all different directions
in various parts of space
that's what will happen according to the
newtonian theory of gravity
now according to einstein's theory
general relativity
if the sun were to disappear it would
take eight minutes for earth
to know about it because the speed of
light
says that it takes about eight minutes
roughly eight minutes
for light from the sun to reach the
earth so if the sun were to disappear
we would not know about it for eight
minutes
and it's only after eight minutes that
the gravitational
effect or or the sudden gravitational
disappearance of the sun would be
uh would have an impact on us so it's
only after eight minutes that the earth
would fly off
and it would take longer for the other
planets like jupiter and saturn
to know about the fact that the sun has
disappeared and only then would they
start flying off in different directions
so that is the difference my friends
between
newtonian gravity and general relativity
general relativity
general relativity like i said it treats
uh
the fabric of universe as a
four-dimensional space-time
and this is the difference between
general relativity and newtonian gravity
general relativity is much more accurate
than newtonian gravity uh we can still
use newtonian mechanics to send
a rocket to the moon and bring it back
safely we can send people to the moon
and bring them back safely without using
general relativity
using just newtonian mechanics so it is
pretty accurate
but there are certain phenomena that it
can't
account for and that is where general
relativity comes in it is an
improvement a significant improvement on
newton's theory
of gravitation so that in in very brief
is what relativity is it is a theory of
gravitation
it is an improvement upon newton's
theory of gravity
and things such as gps and much more
would not have been possible
had we not discovered general
relativity so that in brief
is what it is good question sir
akash asks uh do you think dyson spheres
are scientifically possible to build
even if a civilization
develops immensely
so there is definitely uh nothing in the
laws of physics that
would prevent a sufficiently advanced
civilization from
from building a dyson sphere so let me
show you what a dyson sphere is
this is a hypothetical artist's
representation of a dyson sphere
it is a sphere that envelops an entire
star
it is a monumental piece of of
engineering
it is a sphere that envelops an entire
star
this thing will close around the star
and it will be basically
basically be able to harness the entire
energy output
of that star so that's what a dyson
sphere is this is a hypothetical
representation
this is another hypothetical
representation of a dyson
swarm kind of uh structure being
constructed around a star so the the
objective of such a hypothetical
structure is
to hardness the total energy output of a
star
so you would need to be a very advanced
civilization
to be even able to think of constructing
something like that
so it's a very uh you would need to be a
very advanced civilization there is
nothing against the laws of nature
against the law
in the laws of physics that says we
can't build it but
can a civilization reach that uh level
of advancement
well we are nowhere near it we are not
nowhere near near even
being able to harness the total energy
of our own planet we can't control the
weather
and there are so many things that we
have no control over
we are trying to do it we are doing a
very bad job of it right now but
so we are very far from it is it
possible theoretically
certainly so there was this uh thing in
the news
a star that was that was uh exhibiting
very erratic
patterns of dimming and brightening it's
called tabby's
star tabby's star uh i don't have it
here open somewhere
but uh look it up it's called tabastar
it's a star
which is about a few hundred light years
from the earth
and it has this pattern or non
pattern of erratically brightening and
dimming the dimming affects
about 27 percent of the light output of
the star so that that is very
considerable dimming
and as of today we have no nat we have
no
uh proper explanation of what could be
the process that is causing this
erratic dimming and brightening up of
the star
so if there was some large planet or
swarm of dust or form of comets orbiting
the star
then this dimming and brightening would
be periodic
it would be periodic and we could we
would be able to predict it
but in this in the case of the star it
is not predictable at all
uh in 2017 or 18 it this this
these events were very the
brightening and dimming was very market
very noticeable
right now it's not there much at all so
it is a very erratic pattern
and some people have hypothesized that
somebody is building a dyson sphere
or dyson swarm or dyson ring around
this particular star and that
possibility has not yet been
ruled out because there is no well
accepted
natural explanation of what's going on
in the star so that could be a
possible candidate possible candidate
there's a small chance it could be
something like
another another civilization creating
constructing something
something around the star we don't have
proof it's a hypothetical possibility
but it is certainly a possibility that
is being considered
so that's the deal it could be possible
but we have never observed any real
evidence
this is possible tentative uh
perhaps evidence that perhaps something
like that may be going on
but perhaps there is a natural
explanation too
that we are still not able to figure out
so yes it is a possibility
but it is uh it is not anywhere
near possible near near near to possible
for us because we are still so
underdeveloped technologically as a
species
but theoretically yes definitely
possible
okay loop quantum gravity for a
dilettante
so that's a good question what is loop
quantum gravity
so according to so loop quantum gravity
is
a quantum theory of of gravitation it's
a quantum theory of space-time
so according to general relativity like
i said space-time is this
four-dimensional fabric
in which inside which events occur
so it is the stage or the platform or
the arena upon which various events
occur
in our universe and even in string
theory the space is the background on
which
strings vibrate one dimensional string
strings
so this is a new theory it says that the
geometric fabric of space-time is not
continuous
it is itself quantized it is made up of
discrete quanta of space-time bits of
space-time
so that's what loop quantum gravity says
and it says that
distance itself has a minimum quantity
which is 10 raised to minus 20 minus 33
centimeters
and this center this theory says that
time itself is quantized
time 2 has a minimum quantity 10 raised
to minus 43 seconds
and according to loop quantum gravity
lqg
the name suggests loops so it says that
space-time
is made up of finite loops extremely
small loops
and the intersection of these loops is
where these
quantum volumes of space reside
each volume is 10 raised to minus 99
centimeters in size it's a very very
very small volume of space
so the intersection of these finite
loops is where these quantum volumes of
space reside
and in the terminology of this theory
large quantities of these loops
of space time are called spin networks
spin networks so space is defined by the
geometry
of these spin networks of the spin
network
and time is defined by the movements
that rearrange the spin network so time
is an
emergent property of the geometry
of the spin network it it emerges when
the spin network moves
and this spin network when it is
combined with the uh
with the quantum movements that is time
so the spin network
when combined with its movements is
called the spin form
so time is quantized in the spin form
it ticks like a clock and each tick is
10 raised to minus 43
seconds long and mass
and energy distort shapes and volumes
of the spin network so this distorts
space and time because any movement of
these quanta
also affects the time quanta so time
is the movements of this volume quanta
and the distortion of space and time
is what we perceive as gravity
so that is lqg loop quantum gravity in a
nutshell it says the whole universe is a
spin network
so lqg loop quantum gravity predicts a
big bounce
it says that the universe will not have
a will essentially
bounce back if it contracts because see
according to the big bang theory what we
have is that
the universe is supposed to have been
have originated as a
zero dimensional point like structure a
singularity
and according to lqg the smallest
allowed volume of space is 10 raised to
minus 99
cubic centimeters so because of that
singularity or is not possible and
therefore the universe
in the future will contract again and
then it will bounce back and
explode so to say or expand violently
or very very very fast in an event that
will look like a big bang
so it predicts a big bounce cosmology so
essentially
loop quantum gravity is able to in a way
tell you what happened before the big
bang
there was a big crunch kind of a big
collapse
a big crunch so the previous universe
the previous
incarnation of our universe contracted
upon itself after a period of time
and it went down to this minimum allowed
quantum of volume
10 raised to minus 99 cubic centimeters
and then it bounced back
so that's what lqg says is it proven no
as of now we don't have sufficient proof
of it
it is a good theory it is a theory that
is taken seriously
and it needs to be refined further and
it is to make predictions that are
testable
as of now we don't have any significant
testable predictions
but it's a very good and very
interesting theory
so that is loop quantum gravity in
in a nutshell it's a great question
okay this is another great question do
the laws of the universe
also change with time so
how do i interpret what you're asking
basically what you're asking is two
different things
firstly do the equations of quantum
mechanics in quantum field theory
and do the equations of general
relativity do these equations themselves
change with time
so that is part one of your question and
part two is
do the strengths of the forces
of nature change with time so we know
about four forces of nature
the strong nuclear force the weak
nuclear force electromagnetism
and the force of gravitation these are
four forces that we know of there may be
others that we don't know of
so do the strengths of these forces also
change with time
that's the so these are two questions
you're asking so as far as we know the
equations that
govern quantum mechanics quantum field
theory
and the equations of general relativity
as far as we know to the best of our
knowledge
they do not appear to change with time
so to the best of our knowledge no to
that part of the question
do the does the strength of the forces
do the strengths of the forces change
with time
it appears that it does so we know that
it is known for a fact i mean
it is known strongly known i could i
would say
it's known that uh in the very
so the best theory that we have tells us
that in the very
initial moments of the after the big
bang all four forces
had the same strength and then various
forces decoupled
so that was the time when you had grand
unification
all four forces were combined into one
single unified force
and that is the grand unified theory
that everyone is all
physicists are are seeking that is the
that is the end point of physics though
so to say one equation that governs the
entire universe
so so at the very beginning that in the
very first moments of that after the big
bang
it is believed that all four forces had
the same strength they were combined
into one single unified force
and then the various forces decoupled
and they are
they acquired different strengths and
gravitation the force of gravity
is today the weakest force of all it is
it is many many orders of magnitude
weaker than the nearest comparable force
so that is what we know so definitely we
know that these strengths of the forces
have changed
since the initial moments after the big
bang now what is also
known right now is that the strength of
the electromagnetic force seems to be
different
very in in very small amounts in
different parts of the universe
there is something called the fine
structure constant it is denoted by the
letter alpha the greek letter alpha
so this fine structure constant
quantifies
the strength of the electromagnetic
interaction so it is essentially a
measure of the strength
of the electromagnetic force and
over the past decade or so there have
been hints
various observations from observations
that the strength of the find
the the uh the fine structure
constant which is the number it its
value may be different to a very small
degree
in different parts of the universe so it
may kind of
uh indicate that the laws of nature
the strengths of the forces may be
different in different parts of the
universe
it is a tentative finding it is not yet
100 confirmed
but it does give telltale
signs or indications that the universe
may be stranger than we actually think
it is
the laws this the forces that we
experience here
may not be the same forces you may
experience in a very far-off distant
corner of the universe
maybe there's a north and south to the
universe itself with different
strengths of the forces so there is
definitely very much a possibility and
it's a very intriguing possibility
so that would indicate that there is
much more to the laws of nature than we
understand maybe we have very
basic rudimentary surface level
understanding
of the laws of nature so that's a very
good question and
we need more data to uncover more about
this but yes there is definitely the
there is definitely data that seems to
indicate that that
the strength at least of the
electromagnetic force may vary
it may be different in different parts
of the universe very interesting
question
akash again the scientific community is
divided on what the
interstellar object
was what are my opinions about it
so what is it is
an object that was discovered in late
2017 i think october 2017
so it's a very strange object it's it
was discovered when it was already it
had already crossed the sun
that already gone around the sun it was
going
away from the sun so here's what this
object
looks like it is an artist's depiction
it's an
artist's representation we don't have
any real images of this thing
but we know it's a general size and and
shape
so it's about probably around 100
kilometers long
it is a thin structure it's a cigar
shaped structure
and here's what we know about it so we
know its size
we know it's it's rough shape and we
know that
after it went around the sun it was in a
hyperbolic orbit
which means that it was it is going to
escape the solar system it's never
coming back
which also means that it came from
outside the solar system it's an
interstellar traveler
it's the first object we have discovered
thus far
which is extra solar in origin it is
from
interstellar space it is not of our of
our own solar system
so here's what we know about it we know
that
uh it did not have any gaseous tail
like a comet would have right
and yet when it passed the sun it was
going away from the sun it actually
accelerated now we see this sort of
thing
very quite often when you have a comet
it gives off gases when it is
uh heated up by the sun's radiation and
this ejection of gases
can cause comets to accelerate or
decelerate or
or it can cause their their orbital
paths to change
so it's very difficult to predict the
exact uh
orbit of a comet because of this reason
so you can
maybe predict the orbit of a comet for
100 or 200 years at most but then it's
it's very
very hard to do that so we found that
this object
exhibited acceleration but it did not
have any
gaseous output it did not have any coma
it did not have any cometary tail
so that is very perplex perplexing there
is no mechanism that ex that explains
why this object accelerated away from
the sun
secondly it is extremely highly
reflective it is at least
10 times more reflective than your
typical
solar system rocky object so some people
have hypothesized that it is a solar
sail
so i discussed solar sails a couple of
questions ago
so some people have hypothesized this
could be a solar sail
or a relic from some ancient
civilization
something that was floating around in
space at a very high velocity
and we happen to find it so it is highly
reflective
maybe it's made of metal and maybe it's
a solar cell
it's its shape is extremely atypical
typically you don't find the objects of
this shape natural objects of this shape
in the solar system
it kind of reminds you of either a solar
say a solar sail
or a spent rocket part like a booster of
a rocket or something
so that's why some very respectable and
serious physicists have
propounded the hypothesis that this
could have been our first contact
with a with an extraterrestrial
civilization
now this object is traveling very fast
it's already too far for us to
really do any kind of uh observations
uh a radio telescope was pointed at this
object for a few hours but
no signals were forthcoming so it's a
big mystery
but uh some very serious and very well
respected
physicists have put forth the very
serious
hypothesis that this could have been our
first encounter
uh with an extra solar with an
extraterrestrial civilization i think it
was avi lube
who's an american israeli physicist who
wrote a book about this even
so it's a very interesting phenomenon
it's a very interesting event and
unfortunately
we are not in a position to send any
probe to
meet up with this object because it will
take time to design and construct such a
thing
by which time this thing will be gone
so from what data we have we don't have
the answer
a very definitive answer but yes it is
very intriguing and it could have been
something
possibly from somewhere else something
that was created by
intelligent beings perhaps so the
possibility is there
i and do take this possibility seriously
but we don't know for sure
so that is where we are at with this
question
siddhant asks can a person study
astrophysics or advanced physics if he
or she doesn't know
complex mathematics or doesn't have a
mathematical background
unfortunately no short answer no you
cannot you cannot study advanced physics
of any kind any field without its horror
understanding of mathematics
this is the basic prerequisite for
studying physics you need to
you need to put in the hours and the
days and the weeks and the months and
the years
studying mathematics of ever increasing
complexity
so that's what physicists have to go
through that is the
that's the price for admission for being
a physicist you have to
study all kinds of math basically it is
calculus differential equations
linear algebra matrices vectors
and various other things you can just
purchase a book of
on mathematical methods of physics but
you have to start at the very basic
level
school high school college level
university level etc
so unfortunately you cannot really study
physics or do research in physics or
comprehend
real physics unless you
put in the time and pay your dues and
learn the math
otherwise you just have to rely on other
people to give you information about
physics
like what i am doing right now or your
favorite uh
personal astronomer or astrophysicist so
that's what
is that's the deal about physics you
really need to know the math
in order to properly comprehend it
and to make your to to come to your own
conclusions about it
instead of relying on the basically the
opinions
or the facts or ideas given by others to
you
so you do have to learn mathematics and
the mathematics can get really complex
at times especially when you are dealing
with uh
string theory or even general relativity
when you have tensor
tensor calculus etc so that is a basic
prerequisite for
doing real physics yes
all right this is the last uh question
i've selected thus far
yash asks please explain hawking
radiation and how will a black hole
vanish
after trillion trillion etc years
so hawking radiation is a very
interesting effect
so what we know about black holes is
this
a black hole is essentially uh an object
who's uh that is so massive
and so compact and so dense that even
light cannot escape from it
not even light can escape from it which
means that
it can but it can absorb mass and energy
what this indicates is that an object
from which nothing escapes
but an object which will swallow or eat
up or observe
absorb mass and energy which means that
an object like this should only be
capable of growing larger
it should never be something that can
decrease in size
that is our understanding of black holes
that's what that's what general
relativity tells us
now what stephen hawking found i think
he had
visited the soviet union and a couple of
soviet scientists told him
that black holes especially rotating
black holes should be capable of
emitting radiation so stephen hawking
applied quantum field theory to
the uh to the edge of black holes to the
space time that is around
the event horizon of black holes and
what he found
was that black holes do emit radiation
so here's one way of looking at it let's
say i have a black hole
okay a spherical object and let's say
this is the event horizon here and the
black hole center is here
now we know from uh quantum field theory
quantum field theory there says that the
entire vacuum of the universe is made up
of
fields of various uh of various kinds
and there is this vacuum energy in there
so the the vacuum of space is steaming
with these virtual particles
particle anti-particle pairs are
constantly being created and
annihilated in accordance with
heisenberg's uncertainty principle
so this this particle anti-particle pair
appears and annihilates very very very
quickly very rapidly
so quickly that it does not violate the
time component
of heisenberg's uncertainty principle so
the entire vacuum of space is actually
teaming with these particle
anti-particle pairs and we have
experimental
confirmation of this casimir effect
so what we know is that you have this in
empty space now at the edge of a black
hole at the edge of the event horizon
let's say a particle anti-particle pair
is formed
now the the energy is borrowed from
space-time itself
and when the they annihilate each other
the energy is given back to space-time
so the net change in energy is zero
let's say a particle anti-particle pair
is formed right
outside the event horizon of a black
hole and it goes into different
directions
and before it can recombine one of the
particles or anti-particle
is absorbed by the black hole because it
crosses the event horizon
and the other one is then free to go
away which means that
from a virtual particle it became a real
particle
right now the energy was borrowed from
space
from from space time from from the
vacuum of space it was supposed to be
given back to the vacuum of space
now what happened is that one particle
went inside the black hole
and the other particle is now available
to us so we have gained the energy of
this particle
which effectively means that to
compensate for this
energy we gained in violation of
heisenberg concentric principle
it means that the particle that went
inside the black hole has
negative energy or mass which means the
black hole actually
shrinks by a little bit when this
happens
and that is the process that is one way
of looking at hawking radiation the the
actual manner is different
this is a good analogy of how this thing
happens
so because of the uh
the creation and annihilation of
particles in space-time
when it happens at the edge of the event
horizon of a black hole
you have these particles that escape
from it and which we see as a flux of
energy
and radiation actually and what goes
inside the black hole has negative mass
so over time the black hole slowly over
time
shrinks so for somebody who is standing
or sitting far away and observing a
black hole
it looks like the black hole is
radiating energy it is radiating
particles it is radiating it is emitting
radiation
and it is this radiation that's called
hawking radiation
this is called black body radiation okay
that is a term that you can look up
so an object like a black hole
actually emits radiation and we know
that anything that emits radiation has a
temperature
so black holes have temperature the
larger a black hole the colder it is
the smaller a black hole the more
radiative it is and the hotter it is so
the thing is
the smaller black hole the more
radiation it emits and the faster it
emits radiation
and the hotter it is and therefore it
gets smaller quicker
so small black holes shrink faster and
faster
until at the very end it explodes in a
burst
of hawking radiation so that is hawking
radiation that's what it is
black holes even though they are dark
even though they are black
they still do emit hawking radiation
by this semi-classical theory of stephen
hawking
have we ever observed hawking radiation
thus far we don't have any
real evidence of it but
theoretically this is what happens so
that is the answer to your question
so how long will a black hole last large
black holes
there they have lifetimes that exceed
the current
age of the universe they could be around
forever and they are so cold that
instead of
emitting radiation they absorb the
cosmic microwave background reduction
and then they grow larger
so black holes beyond a certain size
they are most likely
essentially immortal black holes they
will live
as long as the universe exists smaller
black holes have a finite lifetime
they emit radiation and
so you can calculate what exactly the
temperature and the lifetime of a black
hole is there's a formula for that
so certain black holes are de facto
immortal and some smaller black holes
will eventually
meet their fiery explosive demise
so that sir in brief is what hawking
radiation is
now let me take a couple of live chat
questions
let me see what you have lots and lots
okay not a hurry rao uh thank you for
the super chat
uh roger penrose's conformal cyclical
cosmology talks about eons
where the end of every eon is also the
beginning of another eon
sounds eerily similar to kalpas can i
elaborate
i haven't really studied his theory in
in detail
i think he's written a couple of books
about it and some papers
what i understand is that the universe
keeps expanding and expanding unless it
is
until it is almost completely empty and
then you can
transform the equations of space time
etc
in such a way that it resembles a new
big bang sort of of sorts
so that's what it seems to be i i
personally haven't studied this
particular specific theory
it's an interesting theory it is
definitely a valid theory of
cosmology uh so that's what he calls
eons the universe is a very long life
frame after which it
re-emerges as a new universe as a new
big bang so that's what he calls eons
i'm not sure if it is the same thing as
the kalpas kalpas are
i am not very clear about the
terminology of kalpas so
so i am not sure whether it is the same
thing as that or whether it is similar
to that
maybe what i'll do is i will look up
what exactly kulpers are what the
terminology means
and then maybe i can revisit this
question and i can also
look up roger penrose's theory conformal
cyclical cosmology
so it is essentially the theory of a
cyclical universe there are many other
such models there is also like i said
the big bounce model in loop quantum
gravity
so these are similar models which say
that the universe won't expand forever
but there will be cycles
of big bangs and maybe big crunches or
big bounces
and various other other iterations are
similar to that
so it's essentially a cyclical model of
the universe and
it in a way is similar to ancient hindu
cosmology which also says that the
universe is
has cycles each universe has a brahma
associated with it
and each brahma is a finite lifespan
it's a very long lifespan
maybe in the trillions of years if i'm
not mistaken but it does end
so it's a cyclical cosmology cosmology
which is what our ancient four beers uh
thought about and came up with so if
that
is what you mean by kalpas then yeah it
is similar to that so i will just
reconfirm what
these terminologies mean and then maybe
i can answer it again
in a future episode so thank you for the
question
okay i'll take a couple more questions
ashish asks uh
what's possible relevance of the
asteroid belt versus
with respect to chances of asteroid
excavation in the coming future
how far is it well if we can get to mars
then the asteroid belt is just a hop and
escape away from there
it's not really very far from there so
the asteroid belt like most of us would
know it lies between the orbits of
mars and jupiter it is
most likely the remnants of a destroyed
planet maybe there was a planetary
collision
in the infancy of our solar system
and this uh the material of this planet
was catered all over
and it remains in orbit and that's what
the asteroid belt is it's a bunch of
rocks space rocks
and it is known that some of these rocks
are are
metallic very metallic they contain
great deals of
great great quantities of various metals
some of these space rocks may have more
metal
than all the metal that we have on earth
itself
so yes it is a very
lucrative future in industry
asteroid mining exterior excavation if
we can develop the technology to get
there
maybe we can even tug an ester into
earth's orbit or something like that
possibly and extract various
metals minerals and other resources from
it and
so that would be the next big thing in
in
industry in mining it it could
create trillionaires out of people or
corporations
so it will most likely happen maybe in
the next 50 to 100 years maybe
it will most likely start in that time
period
because we will most likely send humans
to mars in the 2030s
if not before that i think most likely
in the 2030s
we are returning to the moon in just a
few years and then
within the next two three to five years
so the americans are planning to send
humans to moon to the moon the chinese
have plans and
the chinese are tying up with the
russians maybe the russians will also be
involved now we have these plans with
spacex to send people to mars and
by the 2030s definitely within the 2030s
so the next logical step would be to to
explore asteroids
so i think that we could start doing
this by the 2030s or by the 20
40s definitely definitely the
the the beginning will be by 2050 before
but it will become of it it takes time
for an industry to grow and mature
and to reach a stage where it is
commercially
viable so i think definitely within this
century sometime
we could have proper commercial asteroid
mining
so it's definitely there in the future
no doubt about it but it's not
something that we will see in the next
10 20 years but definitely within the
century for sure
okay one more question
all right do you think the future has an
uh rahu raghunath asks this
do you think the future has an effect on
the past just like the past has an
immediate effect on the present and
future einstein's block
universe explored explores this einstein
gave us the
theory of relativity i don't know what
block universe is maybe
it's it's maybe it's a colloquial way of
referring to something
i am not familiar with this term block
universe
the theory he gave us was general
relativity
in general relativity you have causality
you have the possibility of
of wormholes which could possibly
enable you to travel back in time it is
a possibility
we don't know yet if it is feasible and
maybe there are laws in the
universe that prevent such time travel
from happening so as to preserve the
laws of causality
quantum mechanics tells us that there
may be no past present or future
there may be no causality at all so
these are all hypothetical concepts
right now we don't know because we don't
understand quantum mechanics
we know how to use it we know how to use
the equations we know how to solve
problems we know how to
create technology with quantum mechanics
but we don't know
what quantum mechanics is telling us we
don't know what's what is
what it is it's at its very core at this
very fundamental level
so the universe is a very big mystery
right now we don't know if time is an
emergent property
loop quantum gravity says that time is
an emergent property
of the geometry and the motion of the
loops of space time
so this is all out there in the open
right now we don't have any definitive
answers
to the question of past present future
the question of what time is
time itself is and to the question of
whether causality is even a thing or not
so these are the boundaries of reality
that we are exploring this is why
theoretical physics is so
fascinating because there is so much
that we don't know and that's why
we are we are looking into these things
so that's my answer i don't have a
definitive answer
for you physics does not as of today
have any answers
and that's what makes it so interesting
all right my friends
i am i am done with today we have come
to the end of today's episode
thank you very much for your wonderful
fascinating questions
keep asking me we're going to have
another session next week and we're
going to keep doing this
so thank you so much thank you so much i
love the questions you've asked
and i will see you in tomorrow's episode
thank you have a good day have a good
night and i'll see you in the next
episode bye